export const ECONOMICSA2015 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. Economics is regarded as a science because it",
A: "studies laws that govern human behaviour.",
B: "uses scientific method to explain human behaviour.",
C: "makes use of controlled experiments to explain human behaviour.",
D: "makes use of machines to study human behaviour.",
answer: "B. uses scientific method to explain human behaviour.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. Which of the following cannot be described as land?",
A: "Forest",
B: "Diamond",
C: "Roads",
D: "Crude oil",
answer: "C. Roads",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. An outward shift of the production possibility curve shows that",
A: "production is shifting to the right.",
B: "resources are underutilized.",
C: "economic growth has taken place.",
D: "factors of production are moving outward.",
answer: "C. economic growth has taken place.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. The following constitute the criteria for identifying an economic system except",
A: "ownership of resources.",
B: "scarcity of resources.",
C: "method of decision making.",
D: "motivation for production.",
answer: "B. scarcity of resources.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. A disadvantage of the mean as a measure of central tendency is that, it",
A: "is affected by extreme values.",
B: "can only be used for continuous data.",
C: "cannot be used to measure the qualities of a population.",
D: "cannot be determined in grouped data.",
answer: "A. is affected by extreme values.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. Which of the following is not an effect of many middlemen in the chain of distribution?",
A: "Shortage of commodities",
B: "Low retail prices",
C: "Hoarding of goods",
D: "High retail prices",
answer: "B. Low retail prices",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. If the price of flour rises, then bread’s",
A: "demand curve will shift to the left while supply curve will shift to the right.",
B: "supply curve will shift to the left.",
C: "supply curve will shift to the right.",
D: "demand curve will shift to the right while supply curve remains unchanged.",
answer: "B. supply curve will shift to the left.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. Which of the following is not a reason for abnormal demand?",
A: "Price of the commodity",
B: "Goods of ostentation",
C: "Giffen goods",
D: "Rare commodity",
answer: "A. Price of the commodity",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. Increase in production subsidies will shift",
A: "the demand curve to the left.",
B: "the supply curve to the right.",
C: "both the supply and demand curves to the left.",
D: "the supply curve to the left and demand curve to the right.",
answer: "B. the supply curve to the right.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. The market supply curve slopes upwards from left to right indicating that",
A: "producers pay high taxes.",
B: "two commodities can be supplied at the same time.",
C: "at a lower price, less is supplied.",
D: "at a lower price, more is supplied and demanded.",
answer: "C. at a lower price, less is supplied.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. Government revenue will increase if taxes are levied on goods with",
A: "perfectly elastic demand.",
B: "fairly elastic demand.",
C: "perfectly inelastic demand.",
D: "unitary elastic demand.",
answer: "C. perfectly inelastic demand.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. If a given change in price brings about a proportionately larger change in quantity demanded, then",
A: "demand is relatively price elastic.",
B: "demand is relatively price inelastic.",
C: "price elasticity of demand is unitary.",
D: "price elasticity of demand is constant.",
answer: "A. demand is relatively price elastic.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. If the price of a commodity Z falls and a consumer buys less of it, then commodity Z is a",
A: "necessity.",
B: "good of ostentation.",
C: "Giffen good.",
D: "normal good.",
answer: "C. Giffen good.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. In order to calculate total utility (TU) from given levels of marginal utility (MU), one has to",
A: "subtract Mil from TU.",
B: "add MU from the various levels.",
C: "multiply MU by the initial TU.",
D: "divide current MU by previous MU.",
answer: "B. add MU from the various levels.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. Which of the following will not affect the market price of a commodity?",
A: "Increase in demand",
B: "Change in tastes",
C: "Intersection of demand and supply",
D: "Increase in supply",
answer: "C. Intersection of demand and supply",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. All the following are methods of determining prices except",
A: "maximum pricing.",
B: "rationing.",
C: "minimum pricing.",
D: "auctioning.",
answer: "B. rationing.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. The law of diminishing returns relates to",
A: "total utility.",
B: "average utility.",
C: "total product.",
D: "marginal product.",
answer: "D. marginal product.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. By adding all the marginal products at each level of employment of the variable input, we obtain a value equal to",
A: "average product.",
B: "total product.",
C: "average variable cost.",
D: "total cost.",
answer: "B. total product.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. Total cost is obtained by",
A: "adding up the marginal cost at each level.",
B: "dividing the total cost by output at each level.",
C: "adding up the average variable cost at each level.",
D: "adding up the average variable cost and total fixed cost.",
answer: "D. adding up the average variable cost and total fixed cost.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. Which of the following cost curves is not U-shaped? The",
A: "marginal cost curve",
B: "average fixed cost curve",
C: "average total cost curve",
D: "average variable cost curve",
answer: "B. average fixed cost curve",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. Which of the following business organizations is likely to experience disagreements between management and shareholders?",
A: "Co-operative society",
B: "Sole trader",
C: "Partnership",
D: "Joint-stock company",
answer: "D. Joint-stock company",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. Which of the following is not a method of controlling monopoly?",
A: "Preventing mergers",
B: "Indigenization",
C: "Privatization",
D: "Imposing high profit tax",
answer: "D. Imposing high profit tax",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. Which of the following features distinguishes a public limited company from a private limited company?",
A: "Perpetual existence",
B: "Limited liability",
C: "Legal entity",
D: "Sale of shares to the public",
answer: "D. Sale of shares to the public",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. Inflation may occur if there is",
A: "excess supply over demand.",
B: "increase in productivity.",
C: "excessive demand with limited supply.",
D: "increased government spending in a depressed economy.",
answer: "C. excessive demand with limited supply.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. Frictional unemployment occurs when",
A: "there is a change in the technique of production.",
B: "job seekers lack information where jobs exist.",
C: "bad weather prevent work from progressing.",
D: "job seekers have disabilities.",
answer: "A. there is a change in the technique of production.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. Which of the following will increase the demand for labour?",
A: "Increased wage rate",
B: "Labour’s demand for output",
C: "Low wage rate",
D: "Low marginal productivity of labour",
answer: "C. Low wage rate",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. One reason for low agricultural productivity in most West African countries is that",
A: "farmers are not capable of cultivating cash crops.",
B: "it does not provide income to farmers with large families.",
C: "farmers find it difficult getting help from financial institutions.",
D: "it is not the only source of raw materials for agro-based industries.",
answer: "C. farmers find it difficult getting help from financial institutions.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. The movement of labour from one grade to an entirely different grade is an example of",
A: "industrial labour mobility.",
B: "horizontal occupational mobility.",
C: "vertical occupational mobility.",
D: "geographical mobility.",
answer: "C. vertical occupational mobility.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. Ten bags of wheat was bought for 50 by a flour miller were sold for 65. What is the Value Added Tax payable by the flour miller if the tax rate is 5%.",
A: "7.50",
B: "3.25",
C: "2.5",
D: "0.75",
answer: "D. $0.75",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. Which of the following is not a strong basis for trade union’s demand for higher wages? The",
A: "company is making higher profit",
B: "productivity of the workers has increased",
C: "members of the union have high qualifications",
D: "commodity produced by the workers is very essential",
answer: "D. commodity produced by the workers is very essential",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. The difference between the gross domestic product (GDP) and gross national product (GNP) is",
A: "depreciation.",
B: "transfer payment.",
C: "net income from abroad.",
D: "direct taxes.",
answer: "C. net income from abroad.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. Location of firms of an industry is not influenced by",
A: "availability of raw materials.",
B: "existence of other firms.",
C: "nearness to the source of money supply.",
D: "government policy.’",
answer: "B. existence of other firms.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. In national income accounting, the term net is used to indicate that a value",
A: "includes income of foreigners.",
B: "excludes income of citizens.",
C: "includes depreciation.",
D: "excludes depreciation.",
answer: "B. includes income of citizens.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. Which of the following best describes token money?",
A: "Money in the vaults of commercial banks",
B: "Currency and coins in circulation",
C: "Money with face value higher than its material, content",
D: "Coins and notes made of poor quality materials",
answer: "C. Money with face value higher than its material, content",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. An industry is best described as,",
A: "firm that sells a set of closely related commodities.",
B: "a factory that produces different lines of products.",
C: "a group of firms that sell « closely related set of products",
D: "industrial concern that is into production and selling of goods.",
answer: "B. a factory that produces different lines of products.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. In developing countries, a larger percentage of the labour force is employed in the",
A: "trade sector.",
B: "tertiary sector.",
C: "primary sector.",
D: "secondary sector.",
answer: "C. primary sector.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. The main item traded on a stock exchange market is",
A: "treasury bills.",
B: "travellers cheques.",
C: "foreign currencies.",
D: "new shares.",
answer: "D. new shares.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. The proportion of commercial banks’ total assets kept in the form of highly liquid assets is known as",
A: "demand deposit.",
B: "fixed deposit.",
C: "cash ratio.",
D: "moral suasion.",
answer: "C. cash ratio.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. What is the total revenue from indirect taxes?",
A: "686.00 m",
B: "400.20 m",
C: "135.80 m",
D: "100.00 m",
answer: "B. $400.20 m",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. What is the total revenue from non-tax sources?",
A: "400.20 m",
B: "375.20 m",
C: "135.80 m",
D: "75.00 m",
answer: "C. 135.80 m",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. Which of the following is not an objective of economic planning?",
A: "Need to direct economic development of the country towards the desired direction",
B: "Desire to ensure a sustained structural development of the country",
C: "Desire to widen the gap between developing countries and the developed world",
D: "Management of scarce resources in the face of unlimited wants of the citizens",
answer: "C. Desire to widen the gap between developing countries and the developed world",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. In order to control inflation, the government should",
A: "reduce the cost of borrowing.",
B: "buy securities in the open market.",
C: "adopt restrictive monetary policy.",
D: "discourage savings.",
answer: "C. adopt restrictive monetary policy.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. When the demand for foreign exchange exceeds its supply, the value of the domestic currency",
A: "appreciates.",
B: "depreciates.",
C: "remains unchanged.",
D: "expands.",
answer: "B. depreciates.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. The exports of West African countries are mainly composed of",
A: "services.",
B: "raw materials.",
C: "manufactured goods.",
D: "consumer goods.",
answer: "B. raw materials.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. A conscious effort of government to achieve a specific set of goals is",
A: "economic planning.",
B: "economic development.",
C: "economic growth.",
D: "economic target.",
answer: "A. economic planning.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. A country has favourable terms of trade when the prices of her",
A: "exports rise relative to the prices of imports.",
B: "exports fall relative to the prices of imports.",
C: "imports rise faster than the prices of exports.",
D: "imports and exports move in the same direction.",
answer: "A. exports rise relative to the prices of imports.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. The abolition of all forms of trade barriers among member countries while maintaining common external tariffs against non-members is a feature of a",
A: "free trade.",
B: "customs union.",
C: "common market.",
D: "economic union.",
answer: "B. customs union.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. In order to correct adverse balance of payments problem, government should",
A: "reduce tariffs.",
B: "increase subsidies on exports.",
C: "increase tax on local industries.",
D: "reduce personal income tax.",
answer: "B. increase subsidies on exports.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. Which of the following is a benefit to a member country of the World Bank?",
A: "Easy access to long term loans",
B: "Management of foreign exchange",
C: "Mediating in labour disputes",
D: "Financing balance of payments deficit",
answer: "A. Easy access to long term loans",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. Which of the following is an objective of OPEC? To",
A: "prevent fluctuation in prices of all commodities",
B: "protect the economic interest of all countries",
C: "control the level of output of oil",
D: "discover oil in all countries",
answer: "C. control the level of output of oil",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},


]